Guide to the Socialist Party (U.S.) Minutes TAM.056.006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Party (U.S.) Minutes
1900-1936
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Party (U.S.)
TAM.056.006
6 Linear Feet (13 boxes)
The Socialist Party (U.S.) was founded in 1901, bringing together moderate socialists from the Social Democratic Party, and dissident members of the Socialist Labor Party. In 1936 the ongoing differences between the "Old Guard" and "Militant" factions, resulted in a split, with the Militant group retaining the SP name and much of the membership, while the Old Guard faction retained most of the organizational and financial assets. The collection contains subject files primarily relating to various conventions and committees of the New York City local of the Socialist Party, New York State conventions and committees, Jamestown (New York) local, and the Socialist Party's National Executive Committee, and also contains minutes of the Socialist Labor Party convention of 1900. Note: this collection has been microfilmed, and researchers must use the microfilm copy (R-7124, reels 9-10).
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection, with the exception of Box 1, Folders 15-25, and Box 6, Folders 1-6, is available on microfilm (Film R-7124, Reels 9-10) for use in this repository only. Researchers must use microfilm for this collection, except folders listed above.
Provenance
Transferred from the Rand School Archives, 1962.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions, however, patrons must use microfilm (Film R-7124, Reels 9-10) for this collection, with the exception of Box 1, Folders 15-25, and Box 6, Folders 1-6.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Socialist Party (U.S.) was founded in 1901, bringing together moderate socialists from the Social Democratic Party, and dissident members of the Socialist Labor Party. In 1936 the ongoing differences between the “Old Guard” and “Militant” factions, resulted in a split, with the Militant group retaining the SP name and much of the membership, while the Old Guard faction retained most of the organizational and financial assets.
Scope and Content Note
The Socialist Party Minutes, 1900 1936, are organized into 14 subject files primarily relating to various conventions and committees of the New York City local of the Socialist Party. This collection also contains minutes of the Socialist Labor Party convention of 1900 (the "Kangaroo" convention), New York State conventions and committees, Jamestown (New York) local, and the Socialist Party's National Executive Committee. The minutes are arranged in chronological order within each subject file. Each subject file has also been assigned a frame number and has been cited in the complete reel list which follows this description of the arrangement of the collection. The researcher should also note that an error was made in the targeting for this collection. on each frame, the word "Series" appears adjacent to the frame number. This term should actually be interpreted as "Collection".
Of special interest in this collection are the minutes of the Socialist Labor Party convention of 1900, the New York City Central and Executive Committee minutes, and the Socialist Party's National Executive Committee minutes. The Socialist Labor Party convention minutes of 1900 (VI:l) pertain to a meeting in Rochester, New York, which was called by Morris Hillquit and other moderates of the party for the purpose of disassociating themselves from the autocratic and doctrinaire rule of Daniel De Leon. These moderates, known as the "Kangaroos", discussed a number of proposals which supported a merger with the Social Democratic Party. The "Kangaroos" also nominated Job Harriman for President and Max S. Hayes for Vice President. Before the convention adjourned, the delegates passed several resolutions condemning De Leon, protesting the police and military actions in the Coeur d'Ailene mining district of Idaho, and recommending further study on the issue of uniting with the Social Democrats. It should be emphasized that the minutes contain both handwritten notes and typewritten transcripts of the convention proceedings. For each convention session, the typewritten transcript was filmed first and the notes were filmed second. This file also, contains correspondence and telegrams.
The New York City Central (VI:9) and Executive Committee minutes (VI:10) offer the scholar a unique and in depth view of the issues and conflicts which culminated in the Socialist Party schism of 1936. During the late 1920s and early 1930s, the New York City local was possibly one of the most ideologically divided branches within the Socialist Party. The various factions, whether they were the entrenched "Old Guard" or the young and restless "Militants", held strong opinions about the relationship between socialism and labor, the socialist attitude toward the Soviet Union and the "popular front", the distribution of power within the Socialist Party, and the socialist response to fascism. By the mid 1930s, the differences between these factions were so great that the Socialist Party ultimately split.
This intense struggle between the "Old Guard" and the "Militants" is also reflected in the Socialist Party's National Executive Committee minutes (VI:14). The National Executive Committee served as the policy making unit of the Socialist Party. As such, the committee members were responsible for preparing various position papers on issues affecting the party, undertaking organizing drives and speaking tours, and financing major party political campaigns and protest demonstrations. During the early 1930s, this committee, like the New York City local, was unable to function properly because of the disputes between the various party factions. The minutes in this file reflect this dispute and its effect upon Socialist Party policies and the national leader ship. For this reason, it is recommended that the National Executive Committee minutes be used in conjunction with the New York City Central and Executive Committee minutes.
Among the items which were not filmed in this collection are the proceedings of the Socialist Unity Convention of 1901, and the Socialist Party Conventions of 1913, 1919, 1920, 1924, 1932, and 1934. These proceedings are contained in the microfilm edition of the Socialist Party of America Papers, 1897 1964 (series I, Part D Convention Proceedings), published by Microfilming Corporation of America.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged topically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Inventory
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Minutes Books, 1872-1907 (Tamiment 056.1)
New York (N.Y.); Minutes (administrative records); Socialism -- United States.; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933; Socialist Labor Party; Socialist Party of New York
- Papers
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 1, Jan 27, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Film R-7124, Reel 9: Frame VI:1
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 2, Jan 28, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 3, Jan 29, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 4, Jan 30, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 5, Jan 31, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 6, Feb 1, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Day 7, Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Constitution and Resolutions, Jan 27, 1900-Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Platform, Jan 27, 1900-Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Minutes (original discarded), Jan 27, 1900-Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Notes, Jan 27, 1900-Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; Correspondence, Jan 27, 1900-Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 10th Annual Socialist Labor Party Convention: Rochester; N.I. Stone Correspondence, Jan 27, 1900-Feb 2, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New York State Socialist Party Convention: New York City, Jul 4, 1908-Jul 5, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Film R-7124, Reel 9: Frame VI:2
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: First Session, Jul 29, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    not filmed
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Second Session, Jul 29, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Third Session, Jul 30, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Fourth Session, Jul 30, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Fifth Session, Jul 31, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Sixth Session, Jul 31, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Seventh Session, Aug 1, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Eighth Session, Aug 1, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Ninth Session, Aug 1, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Tenth Session, Aug 1, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Socialist Unity Convention, Indianapolis: Eleventh Session, Aug 1, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, General Committee, Jan 13, 1907-Nov 23, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 9: Frame VI:3
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, General Committee, Mar 22, 1909-Mar 23, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Central Committee, Apr 13, 1912-Feb 4, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 9: Frame VI:4
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Central Committee, Feb 13, 1915-Dec 23, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Central Committee, Jan 13, 1917-Dec 23, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, May 7, 1906-Jul 29, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 9: Frame VI:5
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Aug 5, 1907-Apr 27, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, May 4, 1908-Nov 8, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Nov 15, 1909-Aug 16, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Aug 23, 1911-Mar 20, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Mar 27, 1912-Oct 13, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Oct 20, 1913-Jun 29, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Jul 5, 1916-Apr 3, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:5
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Apr 17, 1918-Dec 22, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Jul 6, 1914-Jun 1, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Executive Committee, Jun 9, 1915-Jun 29, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Campaign Committee, Feb 13, 1913-Aug 24, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:6
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, 3rd and 10th Assembly District, Jun 17, 1914-May 4, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:7
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, Convention, Jan 16, 1916-Mar 19, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:8
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 4, 1928-Dec 5, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:9
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 2, 1929-Dec 4, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 8, 1930-Dec 3, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 7, 1931-Dec 2, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 4, 1932-Dec 19, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 11, 1933-Dec 6, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 3, 1934-Dec 12, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Jan 2, 1935-Dec 19, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Central Committee, Dec 7, 1936-Jan 5, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 11, 1928-Dec 26, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:10
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 9, 1929-Dec 26, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 15, 1930-Dec 18, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 12, 1931-Dec 30, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 13, 1932-Dec 28, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 11, 1933-Dec 27, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Tamiment Reel number: R2639 (Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:10
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 10, 1934-Dec 29, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 9, 1935-Dec 30, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Socialist Party, Local New York, City Executive Committee, Jan 7, 1936-Nov 17, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; First Session, May 8, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; Second Session, May 10, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; Convention Dinner, May 10, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; Third Session, May 12, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; Fourth Session, May 12, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; Fifth Session, May 13, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Party, 8th National Convention: New York; Sixth session, May 14, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Socialist Party Convention: Detroit, Jun 1, 1934-Jun 3, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Socialist Party Convention: Detroit, Jun 1, 1934-Jun 3, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Socialist Party Convention: Cleveland, Jul 6, 1924-Jul 8, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Socialist Party Convention: Chicago, Aug 30, 1919-Sep 6, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Socialist Party Convention: Milwaukee, May 20, 1932-May 24, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Socialist Party National Convention: Chicago, May 11, 1913-May 15, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Socialist Party, New York State, Quorums and Special Meetings, Jun 12, 1906-Jan 3, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:11
  - Socialist Party, New York State, Quorums and Special Meetings, Jun 12, 1906-Jan 3, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party, New York State, Quorums and Special Meetings, Jun 12, 1906-Jan 3, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party, New York State, Executive Committee, Jan 21, 1911-Jul 20, 1913 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:12
  - Socialist Party, New York State, Executive Committee, Jan 21, 1911-Jul 20, 1913 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party, Local Jamestown (N.Y.):Minutes of Proceedings against E. J. Squier, Mar 9, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:13
  - Socialist Party, National Executive Committee, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 10: Frame VI:14
  - Socialist Party, National Executive Committee, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Socialist Party, National Executive Committee, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Socialist Party, National Executive Committee, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Socialist Party, National Executive Committee, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Fragile Originals
  - Fragile Originals from Box 1, Folder 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 1 - part 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 1 - part 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 2 - part 1, June 12, 1909 - October 22, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 2 - part 2, November 12, 1910 - March 23, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 3, April 13, 1912 - November 14, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 4, Februrary 15, 1915 - December 23, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 5 - part 1, January 13, 1917 - September 28, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 5 - part 2, December 14, 1918 - December 23, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 6 - part 1, May 7, 1906 - July 16, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 6 - part 2, July 30, 1906 - December 22, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 7 - part 1, Jan 2, 1907 - March 25, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 2, Folder 7 - part 2, April 1, 1907 - Jul 29, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 1 - part 1, August 5, 1907 - October 21, 1907 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 1 - part 2, October 28, 1907 - April 27, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 2 - part 1, May 4, 1908 - September 21, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 2 - part 2, September 28, 1908 - May 3, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 2 - part 3, May 10, 1909 - Novermber 8, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 3, November 15, 1909 - Aug 16, 1911 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 4, Aug 23, 1911 - Mar 20, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 5, March 27, 1912 - October 13, 1913 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 3, Folder 6, October 20, 1913 - April 6, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 4, Folder 1, July 5, 1916 - February 6, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 4, Folder 2, April 7, 1918 - December 22, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 4, Folder 3 through Box 4, Folder 5, July 6, 1914 - November 6, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 5, Folder 1 through Box 5, Folder 4, Jan 4, 1928 - Dec 2, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 5, Folder 5 through Box 5, Folder 12 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 5, Folder 13 through Box 5, Folder 14, Jan 12, 1931 - Dec 28, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 5, Folder 15 through Box 5, Folder 17, Jan 11, 1933 - Dec 30, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 6, Folder 1, May 8, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 6, Folder 2 through Box 6, Folder 3, May 10, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 6, Folder 4 through Box 6, Folder 6, May 12, 1920 - May 13, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 6, Folder 7 through Box 6, Folder 10, May 14, 1920 - June 4, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 6, Folder 11 through Box 6, Folder 13, May 11, 1913 - May 24, 1924 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 1 - part 1, June 12, 1906 - Oct 1, 1907 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 1 - part 2, Oct 5, 1907 - Mar 3, 1908 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 2, March 17, 1908 - June 6, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 3 - part 1, July 20, 1909 - May 3, 1910 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 3 - part 2, May 17, 1910 - Jan 3, 1911 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 4 - part 1, Jan 20, 1911 - June 18, 1911 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 4 - part 2, July 6, 1911 - April 2, 1912 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Fragile Originals from Box 7, Folder 5, May 9, 1912 - Oct 21, 1913 (Box 13, Folder 5)